<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An extract out of the historie of the last French King Henry the fourth of famous memorie according to an autentique [sic] copie written in his life time. To which is added his being murdered with a knife in his coach in Paris the 14. of May last 1610. styl. Rom. With an apprecation [sic] for the safeguard and happines of our most gracious soueraigne Iames the first, &amp;c. Seene and allowed by authoritie.</title>
            <author>Skory, Edmond.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12310</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117438</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852652</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852652</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17985</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12310)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17985)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1008:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An extract out of the historie of the last French King Henry the fourth of famous memorie according to an autentique [sic] copie written in his life time. To which is added his being murdered with a knife in his coach in Paris the 14. of May last 1610. styl. Rom. With an apprecation [sic] for the safeguard and happines of our most gracious soueraigne Iames the first, &amp;c. Seene and allowed by authoritie.</title>
                  <author>Skory, Edmond.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie. Anno 1610. To be sold at Britaine Burse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1610]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Edmond Skory.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A" in a mortised ornament.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The life and death of the French King.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  IV, --  King of France, 1553-1610.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17985:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17985:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17985:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17985:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXTRACT OVT OF THE Hiſtorie of the laſt French King HENRY the fourth of famous memorie, <hi>According to an Autentique Copie</hi> written in his life time.</p>
            <p>To which is added his being <hi>murdered with a knife in his Coach in</hi> Paris the 14. of May laſt 1610. Styl. ROM.</p>
            <p>WITH AN APPRECA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION FOR THE SAFEGVARD and HAPPINES of our MOST GRACIOVS Soueraigne IAMES the firſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ Seene and allowed by Authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Jmprinted at London by</hi> Robert <hi>Barker,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie. <hi>ANNO</hi> 1610.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>To be ſold at</hi> BRITAINE BVRSE.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17985:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17985:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honorable WILLIAM Lord <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſcount</hi> Cranborne, <hi>ſole ſonne</hi> and heire to the Right Honorable the Earle of SALISBVRY, L. High <hi>Treaſurer of England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE continuall <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours</hi> J receiued from your L. at my being in <hi>FRANCE,</hi> doe (and ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes) binde me to ſerue and honor you in what J may. And now pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing with my <hi>ſelfe</hi> to conſecrate to this our <hi>Age</hi> and to <hi>Poſteritie,</hi> the <hi>memorie</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>4.</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:17985:4"/> late <hi>French King,</hi> (whoſe most deplorable <hi>Murder, ſorrow</hi> it ſelfe can neuer ſufficiently bewaile) J eſteemed the <hi>Dedication</hi> thereof, (as well in reſpect of my owne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular dueties to your L. as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the <hi>Qualitie</hi> of the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect,</hi> whereof J write) to belong to you, more then in <hi>Part.</hi> For with whome may my Narrations of the wonderfull paſſages of his <hi>Life</hi> hope to finde more gracious acceptance, then with your L. whom J knew to be ſo great an honourer of his <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> an eye-witneſse of his Royall Parts, and one that had receiued ſo many ample fauours from him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aliue?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Murdered,</hi> (J cannot call it
<pb facs="tcp:17985:4"/> his <hi>Dying,</hi> for they <hi>Die</hi> not, but are <hi>made</hi> to <hi>Die,</hi> who are ſo Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered) are best knowen to your L. whoſe ſpeedie Letters gaue our STATE the firſt notice of his <hi>Fall.</hi> J onely now ſet them downe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to your <hi>Thoughts</hi> the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration</hi> of <hi>Humane frailtie,</hi> and the <hi>Weakneſſe</hi> euen of <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Greatneſſe,</hi> ſo often as you call to minde that <hi>KING,</hi> then whom, the <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian world</hi> cannot haue a more ample or appoſite <hi>Subiect</hi> to meditate vpon.</p>
            <p>It was about <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> last past (your L. did then too through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinke of it J am ſure, euer after to forget it) that the rumour of our <hi>Kings death</hi> was ſpread ouer the
<pb facs="tcp:17985:5"/> 
               <hi>French Court;</hi> which (though it were but a rumour, and against which all thoſe then about you oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelues) ſtrooke you notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo full of <hi>dolour</hi> and <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of ſpirit,</hi> that J ſuppoſe how much your <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>gentle nature</hi> was wounded with the ſight of this <hi>Kings</hi> wounds. Two nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>occurrences,</hi> that in your <hi>Lordſhips Trauels</hi> you ſhould heare of the murder of your owne King, (which prooued otherwiſe) and be an eye-witneſſe of the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of another, which was too true; and both of them the greateſt Kings of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your <hi>Loſſe</hi> in <hi>Him</hi> was <hi>great; great,</hi> in looſing a <hi>KING,</hi> from whom you had receiued ſo <hi>gracious
<pb facs="tcp:17985:5"/> reſpects; great,</hi> in cutting off your <hi>Honourable purpoſe</hi> of follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Fortunes in thoſe <hi>Germane Warres,</hi> wherein you ſhould haue ſeene ſo <hi>warrelike Leſſons</hi> read by ſo <hi>Excellent</hi> and <hi>profound</hi> a <hi>Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>GOD</hi> (whoſe <hi>Prouidence</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> is as <hi>infallible,</hi> as <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtable</hi>) hath diuerted him from finiſhing that <hi>great Affaire,</hi> which he hath left (I hope) to be conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated by <hi>another.</hi> I ceaſe from further troubling your Lordſhip, and ſo rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Euer humbly at your Honors command,</hi> Edmond Skory.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:17985:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17985:6"/>
            <head>AN EXTRACT out of the Hiſtorie of the laſt <hi>French King</hi> HENRY <hi>the</hi> 4. of famous memory.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here being an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Fortune</hi> in the <hi>perſon</hi> of this <hi>French K.H.</hi> the 4, whoſe life I will onely point at; hath iuſtly gotten him all the eleuated <hi>titles</hi> of an <hi>immortall glory.</hi> So many <hi>actions</hi> of his <hi>perſon</hi> are as ſo many <hi>miracles,</hi> and may ſafely exempt him from being <hi>paralleld</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>difficultie</hi> of <hi>obtaining,</hi> or <hi>happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> in <hi>keeping</hi> ſo <hi>great</hi> and <hi>ſtirring</hi> a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> And the <hi>particulars</hi> indeede of the courſe of his <hi>life;</hi> ſeeme by the <hi>Diuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence</hi> to haue bene conducible to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of that <hi>State;</hi> which otherwiſe had fallen into an irrecouerable conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. His <hi>birth</hi> being amongſt the barren
<pb facs="tcp:17985:7"/> rockes: and his <hi>education</hi> comporting with the aſperitie of the <hi>place,</hi> were the ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents with which his <hi>youth</hi> was tempered, and wherby (his <hi>body</hi> as his <hi>ſpirit</hi> made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible) he was prepared fit for the acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of great, and glorious <hi>labours.</hi> Hee had not drawen the breath of ſeuen yeeres in this <hi>world;</hi> but his <hi>qualitie</hi> drewe him into the <hi>knowledge</hi> of the <hi>world:</hi> where, his <hi>royall towardneſſe</hi> begot him <hi>estimation,</hi> and that <hi>eſtimation</hi> (euen then) extended it ſelfe to the aſſured hope of <hi>ſucceeding great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> By the <hi>Ciuil warres</hi> was his <hi>Father,</hi> (the <hi>Light,</hi> &amp; <hi>Conductor</hi> of his <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>fortunes</hi>) extinguiſht; his <hi>Mother</hi> remoued from <hi>Court;</hi> his <hi>Vncle</hi> impriſoned; his friends in diſgrace; his <hi>ſeruants</hi> baniſhed; and his <hi>owne ruine</hi> plotted.</p>
            <p>And now theſe <hi>of the Religion</hi> (beeing wrapped in like extremities, diſpoſing their <hi>eyes</hi> to heauen, &amp; their <hi>bodies</hi> to the earth, finding no other hope of <hi>ſafetie,</hi> then in his <hi>Armes</hi>) elected <hi>him</hi> their <hi>Generall;</hi> the aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hopes of <hi>whom,</hi> by the loſſe of foure <hi>Battels,</hi> could not bee repaired but by the
<pb facs="tcp:17985:7"/> felicitie of his <hi>Generous courage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>nineteene</hi> yeere old he was inueigled into his firſt <hi>marriage;</hi> a marriage as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, as illegitimate; for celebration of which direfull Nuptials; <hi>Hymen</hi> had his garment not ſprinkled; but daubed all ouer with the blood, of the beſt bloods in <hi>France;</hi> his <hi>Mother</hi> loſt her life, his <hi>friends</hi> were baniſhed, <hi>himſelfe,</hi> and his <hi>ſeruants</hi> captiued. All which miſchiefes he ſuffred patiently, and vnder-went the perils, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniencies, and labours, (though a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall) euen of the <hi>Common ſouldier,</hi> vntill the time; that his wiſdome obtained to his partie, ſome relaxation of euils; and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from toiles, by the meanes of a <hi>fift Edict of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuddenly; was this calme conuerted into a ſtorme, which powred vpon him the charge of ten <hi>royall Armies</hi> in leſſe then foure yeeres. At the <hi>battell</hi> of <hi>Coutray,</hi> his name was made terrible to the enemie; who, but by ſo apparant merit; was vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to haue acknowledged his <hi>Vertue.</hi> A cruell tragedie ended, where France was
<pb facs="tcp:17985:8"/> the Theatre, ſtrangers the Actors, the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilogue</hi> of which was cloſed with the death of <hi>two Princes,</hi> who had filled the Realme with fire, blood and confuſion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> then reigning <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. (predeceſſor to this <hi>King,</hi> as well in being <hi>murdered,</hi> as in <hi>rule</hi>) being in deſperate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe and almoſt ſurpriſed at <hi>Tours,</hi> was happily reſcued by this H. the 4. whoſe <hi>approach</hi> (like the diſcouery of a Land to <hi>men</hi> long at ſea) inſpired a new courage into the Kings drooping and diſheartned forces, and had conducted him to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted conqueſt of PARIS; but for that execrable King-killing-<hi>Friar,</hi> whoſe <hi>face,</hi> as his <hi>diſseigne</hi> was mufled with the <hi>veile</hi> of <hi>pietie;</hi> by meanes whereof he was ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely rent from <hi>himſelfe,</hi> his <hi>fortunes,</hi> and his <hi>friends:</hi> The true naturall French men (being thus deſolated of their <hi>Prince,</hi> and fearing many <hi>tyrant-Kings</hi> in ſtead of <hi>one-lawfull</hi>) caſt themſelues into <hi>this mans armes,</hi> and did commit to his <hi>vertue</hi> and <hi>valour,</hi> the <hi>reuenge</hi> of their ſlaughtered King, and the ſaluation of their State. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:17985:8"/> to ſuch an <hi>height</hi> was the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the fact growen, and to ſuch an <hi>ebbe</hi> was the fidelitie of the people drawen, by reaſon of <hi>diuerſitie</hi> in <hi>Religion:</hi> that many did ſhamefully abandon him; chuſing rather to be idle <hi>ſpectators</hi> in their <hi>Countries</hi> ruine, then faithfull <hi>Patriots</hi> in procuring, or defending the <hi>Libertie</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>All theſe oppoſitions augmented his reſolution, and were but as ſo many darke cloudes, in which his <hi>fortunes</hi> and <hi>vertue</hi> being inuolued, might in their due time breake forth with the more <hi>aſtoniſhing vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The inſolent obſtinacie of his rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>ſubiects,</hi> made him to haue as many <hi>combats,</hi> as <hi>iourneyes,</hi> and as many <hi>ſieges,</hi> as <hi>encampings,</hi> oppoſing themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him as a <hi>publique enemie</hi> to entrappe him, whileſt he ſought <hi>them</hi> as a <hi>father</hi> his <hi>children,</hi> to gaine them. Within his <hi>tent</hi> were nothing but griefes &amp; anxieties cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by vn-intermiſsiue infidelities, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious deſſeignes, diſcouered euery mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:17985:9"/> againſt his <hi>perſon</hi> and the <hi>State:</hi> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day double combat, double victory: one againſt his enemies, another with his owne, and <hi>himſelfe:</hi> in the laſt of which, vſing a conniuent lenitie, where a ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per inſight into the offences might bring domage. <hi>Diepe</hi> ſerues for example of his <hi>fidelity. Arques</hi> the ſcale to raiſe his <hi>glory. Paris</hi> beleeuing him vanquiſhed, was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſed to ſee him victorious. He made roades into diuers <hi>prouinces,</hi> to confirme thoſe who were falling off. In his paſſage all yeelded to him, and an infinite number of taken-townes receiued a happy proofe of his <hi>puiſſance,</hi> and <hi>moderation.</hi> He retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the ſame ſucceſſe and diligence, to the reliefe of <hi>Meulan,</hi> chaſing away the armie, and the <hi>Generall</hi> of the enemies, that held it beſieged: who a litle after, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ioyned with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> forces, inſtead of diminiſhing their former ſhame, aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented his glory, giuing him new tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs by the memorable battaile of <hi>Yury.</hi> Following this happineſſe, <hi>Vernon, Mante, Melun,</hi> and many other places, were
<pb facs="tcp:17985:9"/> brought to his obedience, as <hi>Chartreſſe</hi> was after, and <hi>Paris</hi> it ſelfe had alſo bin, if his <hi>goodneſſe</hi> had not feared her ruine and deſolation.</p>
            <p>To recount all his exployts, were mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enough for an ample Hiſtorie, and a taske for a perfect Hiſtorian; yet through theſe ſmall lights: may his <hi>conduct, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, diligence, conſtancie, patience, bountie</hi> and <hi>valour</hi> (the eſſentiall parts of a <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi>) be diſcerned.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Aumale</hi> he was prodigall of his own blood to ſaue others. <hi>Roan</hi> brought to extremitie, ſaw him depart from her to encounter Strangers, which hee put to flight; and had hee not bene diſwaded by the counſell of others from the chaſe, they had receiued the reward of <hi>Runne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus neuer beaten, alwayes victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, conducted by <hi>God,</hi> through the pikes of his enemies, and from their clandeſtine machinations, (which a <hi>falſe deuotion</hi> rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed inceſſantly againſt his life) hee diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and ouerthrew the infernall deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeignes
<pb facs="tcp:17985:10"/> of thoſe, who (to the attaining of their licentious and cruell purpoſes) had made <hi>Religion</hi> their vizard.</p>
            <p>But, at length the hearts of the waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring were fortified, and the eyes of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-violently-deuout vnſeeled; who then ſaw the <hi>vniust cauſes</hi> that held them in <hi>rebellion:</hi> Then beganne the <hi>Townes</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> in aemulation one of another, to contend who ſhould offer <hi>first,</hi> or <hi>most</hi> their <hi>Duetie. Meaux, Lyons, Orleans</hi> and <hi>Bourges</hi> firſt in <hi>obedience,</hi> brought him the firſt <hi>honour;</hi> and, the King by his auſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious entrance into <hi>Paris,</hi> got an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall glory of the knowledge of <hi>Lawes,</hi> and <hi>Armes, pardoning,</hi> as well as <hi>vanquiſhing,</hi> forgiuing in a day ſo many people, and rendring and confirming life and libertie to ſo many <hi>Strangers;</hi> who could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelues, but that they were in the iawes of <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The particular ſieges of <hi>Laon,</hi> and <hi>La-Fere,</hi> the ſcite and qualitie of the gariſon being impregnable, the voyage of the <hi>Franch-comte,</hi> the combats of <hi>Fountaine-François,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17985:10"/> the taking of <hi>Dijon,</hi> and other Townes of <hi>Burgongne,</hi> the ſubmiſsion of many Princes, the reduction of <hi>Roan, Newhauen, Amyens, Abbeuille, Peronne, Poitiers, Perigueux, Tholouſe, Marſeillis, Vienne, Valence, Troy, Sens, Rhejms,</hi> and other Townes following their example, will one day fill many volumes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre vpon this Prince the <hi>Laurels</hi> of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> the <hi>triumphes</hi> of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and the <hi>fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licities</hi> of <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At his <hi>generall aſſembly</hi> held at <hi>Roane,</hi> he furniſht himſelfe by the aduiſe of <hi>ſome,</hi> for the Sauegard of <hi>all;</hi> and authoriſed thoſe <hi>edicts</hi> which aſſured <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſurpriſe of <hi>Amyens,</hi> in liew of bearing ill will, the <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> confirmed the <hi>diuine aſsiſtance,</hi> the <hi>fidelitie</hi> of the <hi>French,</hi> the <hi>courage</hi> of the <hi>Prince,</hi> and the <hi>terror</hi> of the <hi>Strangers,</hi> who aſtoniſhed at his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in this buſineſſe; eſteemed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues fairely bleſſed, to haue obtained a peace from him. The <hi>obstinacie</hi> of <hi>Britanie</hi> had giuen matter for his <hi>power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Iuſtice</hi> to worke vpon, if the <hi>prayers</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17985:11"/> of his <hi>friends,</hi> and the teares of the <hi>van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed,</hi> had not diuerted his iuſt diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And then to giue <hi>France</hi> an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and glorious repoſe, and to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution to the <hi>State</hi> of that which had beene taken from her, hee diſplayed his Floure-de-lices within the <hi>Alpes,</hi> ouertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all interpoſed obſtacles. The proude rocke of <hi>Mountmeliend</hi> (which the people thereabout held impregnable) looked fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full at his preſence, and humbled it ſelfe to the force of his Cannons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Piedmont,</hi> doubting her taking, and <hi>Millaine</hi> ſuffring a neighbour-feare (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a frontier) implored the <hi>Pope</hi> by <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion</hi> to diuert him; at whoſe <hi>ſollicitation</hi> he was content to deſiſt from further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution; and to <hi>conſecrate</hi> to the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>good</hi> of that part of <hi>Europe,</hi> his <hi>iuſt anger</hi> &amp; <hi>conqueſts,</hi> if he had followed his <hi>courage,</hi> his <hi>puiſsance,</hi> and <hi>good fortune.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To make all perfect, hee eſpouſed the <hi>Princeſſe Maria</hi> de <hi>Medices,</hi> whome the <hi>heauens</hi> had deſigned to be the <hi>ornament</hi> of <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>Florence,</hi> the <hi>Luſtre</hi> of her
<pb facs="tcp:17985:11"/> 
               <hi>houſe,</hi> and the <hi>hope</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> with <hi>whome</hi> he made his royall entrie into <hi>Paris,</hi> and thinking he had now triumphed ouer <hi>all</hi> the <hi>enemies</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> he diſpoſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to recompence the <hi>merits</hi> and <hi>vertues</hi> of <hi>thoſe,</hi> who had formerly wel ſerued him; howbeit the ingratitude of <hi>one</hi> whome he had mightily raiſed, exaſperating his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, conſtrained him to deliuer him to the <hi>puniſhment</hi> of <hi>death,</hi> whom no other <hi>caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> could reduce to <hi>amendment;</hi> giuing, by this correction of <hi>one; feare</hi> and <hi>example</hi> to <hi>all.</hi> His watchfulneſſe, ſtirred by this <hi>allarume;</hi> he preuented and diſsipated the remainders of that <hi>treaſon,</hi> iniecting a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient terrour into the towne of <hi>Sedan,</hi> by the onely claſh of his armour, who found in their <hi>teares</hi> more ſafetie then in their <hi>rampiers;</hi> and ſo were aſſumed into his <hi>fauour.</hi> By this excellent <hi>example</hi> he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the <hi>good</hi> in obedience, reduced <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> to duetie, and blotted out all remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their former enormous offences; preferring <hi>Mercie</hi> before <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie</hi> before <hi>Profit.</hi> He reeſtabliſht by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne
<pb facs="tcp:17985:12"/> 
               <hi>Edicts,</hi> ſuch as were condemned, and baniſhed by <hi>Arreſt,</hi> and raſed thoſe <hi>monuments,</hi> ſacred to his <hi>memorie,</hi> becauſe they were erected to the <hi>infamie</hi> of <hi>others.</hi> So <hi>ſtrong</hi> is he in <hi>himſelfe,</hi> and in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>world,</hi> that the <hi>conclaue</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects him: <hi>England</hi> is in perfect amitie with him, <hi>Almany</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> honours him, <hi>Spaine</hi> feares him, and <hi>Belgia</hi> ſeekes him. And now hee reioyceth in the <hi>labour</hi> of his handes, and in the <hi>tranquility</hi> which hee hath made with the <hi>price</hi> of his <hi>blood,</hi> and from the twentieth yeere of his age purchaſed with his laborious and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous exerciſes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>lawes</hi> &amp; <hi>Arts</hi> enioy a ſweet repoſe, and large increaſe vnder his <hi>Empire,</hi> and a free <hi>commerce</hi> is reeſtabliſhed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his <hi>Kingdome;</hi> he hath adorned his <hi>Cittie</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> with many and excellent buildings, beſides other his particular workes of great Magnificence.</p>
            <p>He ſhewed his peacefull prouidence in <hi>finances,</hi> his iudgement in the choiſe of men, &amp; his <hi>viue-ſpirit</hi> and excellent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb facs="tcp:17985:12"/> of mind and body in all ſuddaine accidents; And ſince he was a <hi>King,</hi> his greateſt enimies cannot iuſtly vpbrayd him with the leaſt breach of contracted friendſhip with any of his neighbours.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, to ſumme vp this Man of men, this <hi>princelike ſouldier, and ſouldier-like Prince:</hi> whoſe royall face is white with <hi>Time,</hi> with <hi>watchings</hi> and with <hi>experience,</hi> and the Laurels which begirt his venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble head, &amp; tooke their roote in his <hi>Caske,</hi> haue beene gathered in the grounds of three <hi>pitched fields:</hi> of 35. <hi>encounters</hi> of <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;</hi> of an hundred and forty combats, and 300. ſieges of places; in all which; his <hi>perſon</hi> ſtriued (if it were poſsible) to haue got the ſtart of his <hi>courage:</hi> For theſe <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> hath the Chriſtian world reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice in the contemplation of ſo able a champion againſt the common enimie: and the French Nation to hold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues happy in hauing ſo excellent a Prince.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17985:13"/>
            <p>BVt now I muſt forſake this groue of <hi>Baies</hi> and <hi>Oliues</hi> (which his <hi>Valour</hi> and <hi>Wiſdome</hi> had planted for my <hi>Pen</hi> to walke in) and addreſſe my ſelfe to ſpeake of his <hi>Death;</hi> in which the <hi>liues</hi> of ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands were intereſſed. And as <hi>He,</hi> who being to ſet his hand to a <hi>Proſcription</hi> of the <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> wiſhed <hi>he had bene ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of letters,</hi> rather then to vſe them in ſuch a funerall affaire: So I proteſt before the knower of all <hi>Hearts,</hi> that I doe vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly wiſh, not onely that I were igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of letters, but that I had alſo loſt that <hi>hand,</hi> with which I write theſe lines, ſo that hee were liuing; and that I had not true matter to write of his inhumane and barbarous ſlaughter, which I will briefly touch in the maine particulars; as being a Subiect in which my ſpirits languiſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they begin to enter, and in which being entred, I haue ſmall delight to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long.</p>
            <p>The King (for explanation of his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt affection to his Queene; and for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of his owne minde) had (before
<pb facs="tcp:17985:13"/> his intended departure for this <hi>Warre</hi>) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſted <hi>Her</hi> with the <hi>Crowne</hi> and <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>Queene</hi> of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Nauarre.</hi> The mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row after which great ſolemnitie, hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to goe to his <hi>Arſenall,</hi> to viſite the Duke <hi>d' Suylly</hi> his Treaſurer, who at that time was in ſome indiſpoſition of body. And notwithſtanding (as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from good place) that hee was diſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from going abroad that day by ſome, as a day markt out by Aſtrologers, to por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend danger to his Perſon: yet he; a ſecond <hi>Caeſar</hi> as well in the courſe of his life as of his death, was little ſwayed with their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, but like a King, and a Chriſtian replied, <hi>That it was an offence to God to giue credit to theſe Prognoſtiques; and that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God to his Guard, he feared no man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That morning, walking in the great gallerie at the Twilleries, hee had beene ſlaine by this villaine, (who to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe peſtered ſomewhat neere his Perſon) but that by ſome then about the King, he was thruſt off, eſteemed onely as ſome rude raſcall. After dinner, about foure of
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:17985:14"/> 
               <hi>ſtorie</hi> of the new King, by whoſoeuer elſe ſhall write it: Only thus much, the <hi>Queene</hi> was proclaimed <hi>Regent;</hi> during the <hi>Kings</hi> minority: the ſtate of <hi>France</hi> yet enioyeth her former <hi>Tranquility,</hi> and <hi>Monſieur Praſlyne</hi> was diſpatched away to the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> to hold ſome <hi>diſcipline</hi> vntill the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the <hi>Dukes</hi> of <hi>Neuers;</hi> and <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The peacefull <hi>Plenty,</hi> and Diſcipline this <hi>King</hi> had brought France vnto: the <hi>great affaire of warr</hi> which he had in hand, the ſumptuous <hi>crowning</hi> of his <hi>Queene</hi> which he had finiſhed; and to be thus ſnatched away from <hi>theſe,</hi> and in <hi>theſe,</hi> by a ſecond <hi>Heroſtratus;</hi> who hath defaced one of the <hi>royalleſt buildings</hi> the earth bare: muſt powre a myriad of the <hi>worlds</hi> cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and the <hi>vengeance</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in full vialls vpon the <hi>Actor</hi> and <hi>deuiſors</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>ſacred perſon</hi> of ſo great a <hi>King;</hi> ſhould be vndone by the hands of an <hi>vnholy Villaine,</hi> and his owne <hi>vaſſaile:</hi> that a <hi>Prince</hi> of the <hi>ſword,</hi> ſhould be but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chered with a <hi>Knife:</hi> that <hi>He,</hi> who had
<pb facs="tcp:17985:14"/> returned victoriouſly aliue, from the head of ſo <hi>many Armies</hi> (where <hi>Death</hi> keepes his open <hi>ſhambles</hi>) ſhould now be robbed of his <hi>life,</hi> by the hands of <hi>only one,</hi> and in the peacefull ſtreets of <hi>Paris:</hi> which were yet warme with the <hi>glory</hi> of his <hi>Queenes</hi> late <hi>Coronation:</hi> is a villenie; that exceeds (if it were poſsible) the <hi>merrit</hi> of <hi>damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I demand euen of the <hi>Diuell</hi> himſelfe (in whoſe <hi>office</hi> all former villenies are enrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) whether the praeceding <hi>Ages</hi> haue begot ſo ſtupendious and wicked a deed: Nay I will demand of his <hi>Aſtrologie;</hi> (wherein he is ſo great a <hi>Maſter</hi>) whether the ſucceeding <hi>Times</hi> can be malignant enough to produce ſuch another?</p>
            <p>Truely I confeſſe; that the <hi>Intention</hi> of the Pouder-treaſon if it had come to <hi>Act:</hi> (by which our <hi>entier State</hi> had beene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely ruined in an <hi>inſtant</hi>) had exceeded this: (for as yet, God be praiſed the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>France</hi> goeth on in her former and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Courſe:) I confeſſe that <hi>Treaſon;</hi> blew vp all other <hi>treaſons,</hi> as it would haue
<pb facs="tcp:17985:15"/> blowen vp all vs: It was the <hi>Diuells Maſter-peece;</hi> deuiſed by <hi>himſelfe;</hi> exceeding all <hi>Thought,</hi> all <hi>Expreſsion;</hi> all <hi>Example.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O How vnthankefull then are we to <hi>God</hi> for that his miraculous preſeruation of our <hi>King</hi> for the <hi>States ſake;</hi> of our <hi>State,</hi> for the <hi>Kings ſake:</hi> Whoſe <hi>Conſtancy</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Iudicious profoundneſſe</hi> in the <hi>controuerſed points</hi> thereof; whoſe <hi>tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> in <hi>gouernement,</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> euen to <hi>greateſt Offenders,</hi> hath giuen vs cauſe to confeſſe the <hi>valew</hi> of ſo <hi>ineſtimable</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> and with publique ſacrifice of <hi>prayers,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune <hi>God</hi> for the continuance of his ſafetie. How can we heare of ſo terrible a <hi>blow</hi> but on the other ſide of the <hi>wall,</hi> and forbeare to fixe our eyes and hearts on him, that diſpoſeth all things, howſoeuer man propounds.</p>
            <p>And whether the <hi>ſpeech</hi> proceeded from ſome <hi>planetary obſeruation</hi> in <hi>forreine parts,</hi> or from ſome <hi>Intelligence</hi> broken forth from out the denne of theſe <hi>lurking-aſſacinates;</hi> yet ſure I am, (and my <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17985:15"/> is of credit) that euen about this <hi>very time,</hi> the like aſſault was ſaid ſhould bee made vpon the <hi>Perſon</hi> of our <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne:</hi> which diuert O <hi>God,</hi> for thy <hi>Holy Names ſake,</hi> who art <hi>King</hi> of <hi>kings:</hi> for <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions ſake,</hi> he is the <hi>nourice</hi> and <hi>protector of Religion:</hi> for <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Humanities ſake,</hi> wee are borne, and muſt liue vnder <hi>him:</hi> preſerue <hi>him</hi> O God, as thy <hi>image</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>man;</hi> as thy <hi>vicegerent</hi> being a <hi>King;</hi> that as thou haſt with a miraculous peace brought <hi>him</hi> to theſe <hi>his owne Kingdomes;</hi> ſo thou wilt euery <hi>night,</hi> and euery <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> ſprinckle his <hi>diademe</hi> with the dew of <hi>Security, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Plenty;</hi> that <hi>poſteritie</hi> may compare his <hi>reigne,</hi> with the <hi>reigne</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> vntill being <hi>full of dayes,</hi> he ſhall quietly lay downe his <hi>life</hi> and reſigne his precious <hi>ſoule</hi> into <hi>thine hands,</hi> and deliver his <hi>Empires</hi> into the <hi>hands</hi> of <hi>thoſe,</hi> who by <hi>thy Lawes,</hi> and by the <hi>Lawes of Nature</hi> are <hi>borne</hi> to inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17985:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17985:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
